A Guide to the Foundation Center of New York records FA023
Rockefeller Archive Center
Foundation Center of New York records
1922-2007 (bulk 1954-1994)
1954-1994
Rockefeller Archive Center
Foundation Center
FA023
1.92 Cubic Feet 173 microfilm reels, 1 half-letter document box, 40 bound volumes
Biographical/Historical note
The Foundation Center was created in 1956 by foundation leaders who felt the need for an independent organization that would collect and make available information about philanthropic and non-profit organizations in the United States and throughout the world. On May 25, 1956, the Foundation Library Center was incorporated as an educational institution under the authority of the New York State Board of Regents. The Center was to gather comprehensive information about foundations, stimulate reporting and accountability where it did not yet exist, and provide "a convenient place where any person may find accurate information about foundations."
F. Emerson Andrews, long-time president of the Russell Sage Foundation, was the first president of the Foundation Center, serving from 1956-1966. He wrote extensively on the topic of philanthropic and non-profit organizations and was a strong advocate for a central information-collecting agency. He was succeeded by Manning M. Pattillo (1967-1970), Thomas R. Buckman (1971-1991), and Sara Engelhardt (1992-2008).
The books, reports, and files of the Russell Sage Foundation formed a core collection of the Foundation Library Center. The Center also purchased photographic transcripts of financial and other data on approximately 7,000 organizations, and it solicited complete annual reports files where they existed. The library opened to the public in late 1956. In 1960, the Center published its first Foundation Directory.
In 1968, the Foundation Library Center changed its name to the Foundation Center. For further information see its website, http://foundationcenter.org, and its publication "Philanthropy in the 21st Century: The Foundation Center's 50th Anniversary Interviews."
Arrangement note
The records are divided into five series:
Series 1 - Administrative Files (1922-2004)
Series 2 - Program and Project Files (1924-1999)
Series 3 - Non-Related Foundation Center Files (1947-1990)
Series 4 - Foundation Center Annual Reports (1956-2007)
Series 5 - Separated Materials.
Scope and Contents note
The records of the Foundation Center span the years 1922-2004, with the majority of the records dating from the mid-1950s, when the Center was created, to the early 1990s. Most of the material prior to 1956 comes from F. Emerson Andrews, the first president of the Foundation Center. Prior to 1956, Andrews had worked at the Russell Sage Foundation, and much of the correspondence relating to the Foundation Center was addressed to him there.
Containing correspondence, annual reports, financial records, publications, clippings, and a large collection of organizational pamphlets, the collection reveals the history of the Foundation Center and its projects, including fund-raising programs, the directories, "Foundation News," and various seminars in technology and other areas of interest. It also provides a history of governmental influence and tax reform in relation to non-profit organizations. The collection contains manuscripts and articles by F. Emerson Andrews on the world of philanthropic organizations, including his book "The Foundation Watcher." It also includes photographs, a Foundation Center video entitled "Foundations: The People and The Money," a scrapbook containing articles on the Congressional tax reform hearings, and transcripts from these hearings.
The Foundation Center collection exists on 173 reels of 35mm preservation standard microfilm.
Conditions Governing Access
Microfilm user copies are open or research.
Separated Materials
Published material that is readily available elsewhere (such as books or transcripts of Congressional hearings)and special format material, including audio and visual materials and computer disks and punch cards, have been separated and retained in their original formats. "Separation sheets" placed within the microfilmed collection will note the existence of this original documentation.
Separated Materials
The following books were removed from the Foundation Center collection and placed in the Rockefeller Archive Center library. They are available for research use.
Andrews, F. Emerson. Foundation watcher. Lancaster, PA: Franklin and Marshall College, 1973. Copy 2: Inscribed by author; autographed. Call Number: 361.7 AND.
America's voluntary spirit: a book of readings. Ed. Brian O'Connell. New York: Foundation Center, 1983. Call Number: 361.7 ROC.
An agile servant: community leadership by community foundations. Ed. Richard Magat. New York: Council on Foundations, 1989. Call Number: 361.8 AGI.
Zurcher, Arnold J., and Dustin, Jane. The foundation administrator: a study of those who manage America's foundations. New York: Russell Sage Foundation, 1972. Call Number: 361.7068 ZUR.
Duane, Thomas David. Opthalmic research: U. S. A.: a comprehensive national survey of eye research. New York: Research to Prevent Blindness, 1965. Call Number: 612.8 DUA.
Layton, Daphne Niobe. Philanthropy and voluntarism: an annotated bibliography. New York: Foundation Center, 1987. Call Number: 361.7016 LAY.
Kiger, Joseph C. Historiographic review of foundation literature: motivations and perceptions. New York: Foundation Center, 1987. Call Number: 361.7016 KIG.
The literature of the nonprofit sector: a bibliography with abstracts. New York: Foundation Center, 1989-1994. Call Number: 361.7016 LIT.
The foundation directory. Ed. David G. Jacobs. New York: Foundation Center, 2003. Call Number: 2nd Floor/361.7025 FOU.
Foundation Center. Annual report. New York, 1956-2007. (Variant Title, 1956-1967: Foundation Library Center annual report.) Call Number: 2nd Floor, Annual Reports.
Foundation Center. Foundation Center: 50th anniversary: knowledge to build on. New York, 2006. Call Number: 361.706 FOU.
Philanthropy in the 21st century. Ed. Mitch Nauffts. New York: Foundation Center, 2007. Call Number: 361.706 PHI.
File Plan note
Former Classification: XVII
Taxation -- Law and legislation -- United States; Philanthropy; Philanthropy, Charity and the Nonprofit Sector; Charities; Charitable uses, trusts, and foundations
- Administrative Files, 1922-2004; 1
  Arrangement note
  This series is arranged in two subseries:
  Subseries 1 - Historical Information
  Subseries 2 - Officer and Committee Files
  - Historical Information, 1956-2004; 1
    Scope and Contents note
    This series contains historical information about The Foundation Center, including staff charts.
    - The Foundation Center, 1956-1966 (Reel 1, Frame 3)
    - The Foundation Center, 1956-1971 (Reel 1, Frame 58)
    - The Foundation Center, 1990-1993 (Reel 1, Frame 338)
    - The Foundation Center - Annual Reports, 1956-2004 (Reel 1, Frame 383)
    - The Foundation Center - 30th Anniversary, November 21, 1986 (Reel 1, Frame 385)
    - Personnel and Organizational Chart, 1967-1968 (Reel 1, Frame 422)
  - Officer and Committee Files, 1922-1998; 2
    Series 1.2 is arranged in two sections:
    A - Officer Files
    B - Committee Files
    - Officer Files, 1922-1998; A
      Subseries A is arranged in 9 parts:
      1 - F. Emerson Andrews
      2 - F. Emerson Andrews and Manning M. Pattillo, Jr.
      3 - Manning M. Pattillo, Jr.
      4 - Manning M. Pattillo, Jr. and Thomas R. Buckman
      5 - Thomas R. Buckman
      6 - William Kirsch
      7 - Marianna O. Lewis
      8 - Nathaniel Spear III
      9 - Trustees (Deceased)
      - F. Emerson Andrews, 1922-1991; 1
        F. Emerson Andrews served as the first president of The Foundation Center, 1956-1966. Before his time at The Foundation Center, he was president of the Russell Sage Foundation. He was very interested in and studied philanthropic foundations. His papers consist of correspondence, manuscripts and other published works, and material relating to the Jellicoe Foundation. The Jellicoe Foundation was a fictitious foundation created by Andrews to see if other publishing houses were copying from The Foundation Directory. If Jellicoe Foundation was in the other directory he knew they copied directly and without The Foundation Center's permission.
        - Albert Carriere, Inc., 1963 (Reel 1, Frame 431)
        - American Cancer Society, Inc., 1947-1958 (Reel 1, Frame 435)
        - American Council on Education, 1945-1967 (Reel 1, Frame 468)
        - American Foundations Information Service, 1945-1959 (Reel 1, Frame 576)
        - American Foundations Information Service - Purchasing Documents, 1956 (Reel 2, Frame 1)
        - American Historical Society and American Society of Church History - Joint Meeting, December 1961 (Reel 2, Frame 30)
        - The American National Red Cross, 1948-1962 (Reel 2, Frame 55)
        - American Philosophical Society - Project on Foundations, 1959-1963 (Reel 2, Frame 134)
        - American Society of Corporate Secretaries, 1950-1956 (Reel 2, Frame 225)
        - Annual Reports - Acknowledgements and Special Comments, 1962-1967 (Reel 2, Frame 253)
        - Annual Reports - Requests for Foundation Center Depositories, 1963-1964 (Reel 2, Frame 288)
        - Associates of Kenneth Rose, 1955-1960 (Reel 2, Frame 381)
        - Association for the Aid of Crippled Children, 1953-1965 (Reel 2, Frame 438)
        - Association of Independent Research Institutions, 1965 (Reel 2, Frame 530)
        - Robert Beach, 1957-1958 (Reel 2, Frame 552)
        - Classifications, 1957-1963 (Reel 2, Frame 560)
        - Code of Practice, 1964 (Reel 2, Frame 671)
        - Confidential Letters to the Trustees, 1956-1967 (Reel 3, Frame 1)
        - Correspondence, 1922-1956 (Reel 3, Frame 196)
        - Correspondence, 1950-1969 (Reel 3, Frame 307)
        - Correspondence, 1970-1978 (Reel 3, Frame 544)
        - Correspondence and Memoranda, 1960-1974 (Reel 3, Frame 737)
        - Cox Committee - Correspondence to Questionnaire, 1953-1956 (Reel 4, Frame 1)
        - "Crazy" Letters, 1964-1965 (Reel 4, Frame 195)
        - Creation of The Foundation Center, 1956 (Reel 4, Frame 242)
        - Merle Curti, 1957-1967 (Reel 4, Frame 256)
        - Depository Libraries - Acknowledgements, 1959-1961 (Reel 4, Frame 343)
        - Depository Libraries - Atlanta, Georgia, 1960-1969 (Reel 4, Frame 590)
        - Depository Libraries - Austin, Texas, 1960-1971 (Reel 4, Frame 717)
        - Depository Libraries - Berkeley, California, 1960-1975 (Reel 5, Frame 1)
        - Depository Libraries - Center for Research Libraries, 1958-1965 (Reel 5, Frame 70)
        - Depository Libraries - Chicago, Illinois, 1965-1969 (Reel 5, Frame 191)
        - Depository Libraries - Cleveland, Ohio, 1960-1969 (Reel 5, Frame 257)
        - Depository Libraries - Kansas City, Missouri, 1959-1969 (Reel 5, Frame 295)
        - Depository Libraries - Los Angeles, California, 1961-1969 (Reel 5, Frame 395)
        - Depository Libraries - Miscellaneous, 1959-1971 (Reel 5, Frame 467)
        - Berrien C. Eaton, Jr., 1947-1962 (Reel 5, Frame 580)
        - Education and World Affairs, 1964 (Reel 5, Frame 782)
        - The English Speaking Union of the United States, 1963 (Reel 5, Frame 797)
        - Foreign Foundations Program, 1967-1969 (Reel 5, Frame 812)
        - Forty Year Old Foundations and Older, 1968-1969 (Reel 6, Frame 1)
        - Harry Emerson Fosdick - Centennial Year, 1978 (Reel 6, Frame 20)
        - Foundations Delinquent in Reporting, 1963-1965 (Reel 6, Frame 41)
        - Foundations Luncheon Group - Correspondence, 1956-1968 (Reel 6, Frame 97)
        - Foundations Luncheon Group - History, 1953-1960 (Reel 6, Frame 371)
        - Foundations Luncheon Group - History, 1961-1976 (Reel 6, Frame 538)
        - Foundations Luncheon Group - Steering Committee Administration, 1957-1966 (Reel 6, Frame 688)
        - Foundation Management Studies - Proposals and Working Papers, 1964-1965 (Reel 6, Frame 721)
        - Foundation Reporting, 1961-1970 (Reel 6, Frame 736)
        - Foundation Service Company, 1958-1959 (Reel 7, Frame 1)
        - Foundation Services, 1963-1968 (Reel 7, Frame 25)
        - Marion Fremont-Smith, 1961-1967 (Reel 7, Frame 50)
        - Ray Garrett, 1951-1956 (Reel 7, Frame 214)
        - Giving in the United States of America in 1969, 1970 (Reel 7, Frame 404)
        - Grants Statistics, 1962-1966 (Reel 7, Frame 440)
        - Handy Associates, Inc., 1958-1960 (Reel 7, Frame 512)
        - House of Representatives - Legal and Monetary Affairs Subcommittee, 1958 (Reel 7, Frame 535)
        - International Philanthropy - A Compilation of Grants by U.S. Foundations, 1979 (Reel 7, Frame 544)
        - Library of Congress, 1931-1963 (Reel 7, Frame 828)
        - Joseph C. Kiger, 1953-1958 (Reel 8, Frame 1)
        - Materials for Directory, 1958-1967 (Reel 8, Frame 163)
        - Meeting of Depository Librarians, 1961-1966 (Reel 8, Frame 277)
        - Meeting of Depository Librarians, February 6, 1969, 1968-1969 (Reel 8, Frame 345)
        - Memoranda, 1956-1967 (Reel 8, Frame 422)
        - Memoranda to File, 1953-1959 (Reel 8, Frame 594)
        - Memoranda to File, 1960-1963 (Reel 9, Frame 1)
        - Memoranda to File, 1964-1969 (Reel 9, Frame 277)
        - Memoranda to File, 1970 (Reel 9, Frame 674)
        - The Merrill Center for Economics, 1961 (Reel 9, Frame 713)
        - Mid-Continent Conference on Philanthropy, 1963-1964 (Reel 9, Frame 721)
        - Midwest Foundations Information Service, 1964 (Reel 9, Frame 779)
        - National Association of Social Workers, 1949-1963 (Reel 10, Frame 1)
        - National Bureau of Economic Research, 1951-1965 (Reel 10, Frame 176)
        - National Conference on the Administration of Research, September 9-11, 1964, 1964-1966 (Reel 10, Frame 276)
        - National Council of Churches, 1950-1966 (Reel 10, Frame 291)
        - National Council of the YWCA, 1951-1958 (Reel 10, Frame 669)
        - National Foundation for Infantile Paralysis, 1945-1953 (Reel 10, Frame 702)
        - National Opinion Research Center, 1950-1953 (Reel 11, Frame 1)
        - National Planning Association, 1951-1963 (Reel 11, Frame 240)
        - National Science Foundation, 1952-1968 (Reel 11, Frame 286)
        - National Science Foundation Survey, 1961-1963 (Reel 11, Frame 514)
        - National Social Welfare Assembly, 1949-1964 (Reel 11, Frame 681)
        - New Jersey Superior Court - Smith vs. Barlow, 1952-1953 (Reel 12, Frame 1)
        - New York State Legislative Committee on Investigation of Foundations and Charitable Organizations, 1953-1956 (Reel 12, Frame 239)
        - New York University - Conference on Charitable Foundations, 1952-1953 (Reel 12, Frame 346)
        - Office Memoranda, 1958-1967 (Reel 12, Frame 373)
        - Patman Hearings, 1964 (Reel 12, Frame 479)
        - Wright Patman and Patman Questionnaire #1, 1961-1966 (Reel 13, Frame 1)
        - Wright Patman - Select Committee on Small Business, 1961-1969 (Reel 13, Frame 222)
        - Private Agencies- Washington, D. C., 1944-1964 (Reel 13, Frame 309)
        - Private Philanthropy and Public Institutions, 1955-1956 (Reel 13, Frame 373)
        - Proceedings of the Conference on Foundations, January 18, 1957 (Reel 13, Frame 420)
        - Statistics, 1955-1967 (Reel 13, Frame 494)
        - Study of the Foundation Administrator, 1968-1973 (Reel 14, Frame 1)
        - United States Department of State, 1955-1967 (Reel 14, Frame 426)
        - Study of Philanthropic Foundations, 1952-1977 (Reel 14, Frame 430)
        - Surveys and Research Corporation, 1957-1958 (Reel 14, Frame 495)
        - United States Department of Justice, 1951-1952 (Reel 14, Frame 509)
        - United States Department of Labor, 1950-1954 (Reel 14, Frame 517)
        - United States House of Representatives, 1953-1966 (Reel 14, Frame 551)
        - United States Senate, 1949-1965 (Reel 14, Frame 628)
        - United States Treasury Department, 1959-1967 (Reel 15, Frame 1)
        - United States Treasury Department - Informal Advisory Group on Tax-Exempt Foundations, 1963-1964 (Reel 15, Frame 159)
        - University of Pennsylvania Meeting, 1959-1965 (Reel 15, Frame 365)
        - University of Wisconsin - Seminar, 1958 (Reel 15, Frame 394)
        - Virginia Law Review, 1950-1960 (Reel 15, Frame 416)
        - The Washington Center for Metropolitan Studies, 1962-1963 (Reel 15, Frame 466)
        - Western Reserve University, 1960-1961 (Reel 15, Frame 502)
        - Manuscripts and Other Published Works, undated (Reel 15, Frame 572)
        - Manuscripts and Other Published Works - Administration of Foundations, undated (Reel 15, Frame 573)
        - Manuscripts and Other Published Works - American Foundations - Reports to Shelby M. Harrison, 1945-1948 (Reel 15, Frame 613)
        - Manuscripts and Other Published Works - American Foundations for Social Welfare, 1945-1948 (Reel 15, Frame 654)
        - Manuscripts and Other Published Works - Bibliography of Reprinted Articles, 1934-1973 (Reel 15, Frame 831)
        - Manuscripts and Other Published Works - Cited Articles, 1957-1958 (Reel 15, Frame 835)
        - Manuscripts and Other Published Works - Classifications in Philanthropy - Prepared for the Ford Foundation, 1955-1956 (Reel 16, Frame 1)
        - Manuscripts and Other Published Works - Copyright, 1973-1991 (Reel 16, Frame 100)
        - Manuscripts and Other Published Works - Corporate Giving - Preface-Chapter 3, 1951-1952 (Reel 16, Frame 129)
        - Manuscripts and Other Published Works - Corporate Giving - Chapter 4-Chapter 10, 1951-1952 (Reel 16, Frame 252)
        - Manuscripts and Other Published Works - Corporate Giving - Chapter 11-Appendix B, 1951-1952 (Reel 16, Frame 435)
        - Manuscripts and Other Published Works - Corporate Giving - Appendix C-Table 3, 1951-1952 (Reel 16, Frame 582)
        - Manuscripts and Other Published Works - Corporate Giving - Source Material, 1950-1952 (Reel 16, Frame 703)
        - Manuscripts and Other Published Works - The Foundation Directory - First Edition, 1958-1960 (Reel 17, Frame 1)
        - Manuscripts and Other Published Works - The Foundation Directory - Second Edition, 1963 (Reel 17, Frame 119)
        - Manuscripts and Other Published Works - The Foundation Directory - Third Edition, 1967 (Reel 17, Frame 203)
        - Manuscripts and Other Published Works - Foundation Watcher - Published Book, 1973 (Reel 17, Frame 310)
        - Manuscripts and Other Published Works - Foundation Watcher - Chapter 1-10, 1973 (Reel 17, Frame 312)
        - Manuscripts and Other Published Works - Foundation Watcher - Chapter 11-17, 1973 (Reel 17, Frame 485)
        - Manuscripts and Other Published Works - Foundation Watcher - Chapter 18-Appendicies, 1973 (Reel 17, Frame 624)
        - Manuscripts and Other Published Works - National Science Foundation - Tables, undated (Reel 17, Frame 698)
        - Manuscripts and Other Published Works - Occasional Papers - "The Foundation in the Year 2000" by Alan Pifer - Correspondence and Responses, 1968 (Reel 17, Frame 702)
        - Manuscripts and Other Published Works - Occasional Papers - "Foundation Reports to the Internal Revenue Service" - Correspondence, 1969-1970 (Reel 17, Frame 761)
        - Manuscripts and Other Published Works - Occasional Papers - "Foundation Reports to the Internal Revenue Service" - Manuscript, 1970 (Reel 17, Frame 777)
        - Manuscripts and Other Published Works - Occasional Papers - General Correspondence, 1968-1970 (Reel 17, Frame 839)
        - Manuscripts and Other Published Works - Occasional Papers - Barry D. Karl, 1969-1971 (Reel 17, Frame 941)
        - Manuscripts and Other Published Works - Occasional Papers - Manuscripts, 1968-1970 (Reel 18, Frame 1)
        - Manuscripts and Other Published Works - Occasional Papers - Mary Kiley Manuscript, 1970 (Reel 17, Frame 246)
        - Manuscripts and Other Published Works - Occasional Papers - "The Modern Foundation: Its Dual Character, Public and Private" by Milton Katz - Correspondence and Responses, 1968-1970 (Reel 18, Frame 250)
        - Manuscripts and Other Published Works - Occasional Papers - Organizations and Individuals Who Receive Multiple Copies, undated (Reel 18, Frame 315)
        - Manuscripts and Other Published Works - Occasional Papers - "Patman and Foundations: Review and Assessment" - Correspondence and Responses, 1968-1969 (Reel 18, Frame 317)
        - Manuscripts and Other Published Works - Occasional Papers - J. Kellum Smith, Jr., 1970 (Reel 18, Frame 503)
        - Manuscripts and Other Published Works - Patman and Foundations: Review and Assessment, 1963 (Reel 18, Frame 540)
        - Manuscripts and Other Published Works - Philanthropic Foundations - Forward-Chapter 3, 1954-1955 (Reel 18, Frame 623)
        - Manuscripts and Other Published Works - Philanthropic Foundations - Chapter 4-Chapter 7, 1954-1955 (Reel 18, Frame 794)
        - Manuscripts and Other Published Works - Philanthropic Foundations - Chapter 8-Chapter 11, 1954-1955 (Reel 19, Frame 1)
        - Manuscripts and Other Published Works - Philanthropic Foundations - Chapter 12-Bibliography, 1954-1955 (Reel 19, Frame 174)
        - Manuscripts and Other Published Works - Philanthropic Foundations - Source Material, 1948-1955 (Reel 19, Frame 348)
        - Manuscripts and Other Published Works - Philanthropic Giving - Source Material, 1949 (Reel 19, Frame 530)
        - Manuscripts and Other Published Works - Philanthropy in the United States - Second Edition, 1978 (Reel 19, Frame 739)
        - "Who Said That?", undated (Reel 19, Frame 791)
        - Jellicoe Foundation, undated (Reel 19, Frame 801)
        - Jellicoe Foundation - Correspondence, January-July 1964 (Reel 19, Frame 802)
        - Jellicoe Foundation - Correspondence, August-December 1964 (Reel 20, Frame 1)
        - Jellicoe Foundation - Correspondence, January-March 1965 (Reel 20, Frame 141)
        - Jellicoe Foundation - Correspondence, April-June 1965 (Reel 20, Frame 310)
        - Jellicoe Foundation - Correspondence, July-September 1965 (Reel 20, Frame 430)
        - Jellicoe Foundation - Correspondence, October-December 1965 (Reel 20, Frame 583)
        - Jellicoe Foundation - Correspondence, January-March 1966 (Reel 21, Frame 1)
        - Jellicoe Foundation - Correspondence, April-June 1966 (Reel 21, Frame 249)
        - Jellicoe Foundation - Correspondence, July-September 1966 (Reel 21, Frame 523)
        - Jellicoe Foundation - Correspondence, October-December 1966 (Reel 21, Frame 675)
        - Jellicoe Foundation - Correspondence, January-May 1967 (Reel 22, Frame 1)
        - Jellicoe Foundation - Correspondence, June-December 1967 (Reel 22, Frame 212)
        - Jellicoe Foundation - Correspondence, 1968 (Reel 22, Frame 296)
        - Jellicoe Foundation - Correspondence, 1969-1970 (Reel 22, Frame 467)
        - Jellicoe Foundation - Memoranda, 1962-1972 (Reel 22, Frame 540)
      - F. Emerson Andrews and Manning M. Pattillo, Jr., 1945-1972; 2
        - The American Alumni Council, 1952-1968 (Reel 22, Frame 548)
        - The American Alumni Council - Airlie Symposium on Education Fund-Raising and Taxation, February 7-8, 1966 (Reel 22, Frame 704)
        - The American Association of Fund-Raising Counsel, Inc., 1954-1970 (Reel 23, Frame 1)
        - The American Association of Fund-Raising Counsel, Inc., undated (Reel 23, Frame 362)
        - The American Association of Fund-Raising Counsel, Inc. - East/West Conference, May 13-14, 1970 (Reel 23, Frame 397)
        - American Association for Higher Education, 1955-1970 (Reel 23, Frame 416)
        - American College Public Relations Association, 1962-1969 (Reel 23, Frame 790)
        - American College Public Relations Association - Conference, July 1969 (Reel 23, Frame 876)